okay so this is the last lecture for the
好了，所以这是 对 上一讲
class and I'm sure that you've got a lot
一流的，我敢肯定，你已经得到了很多
of other things going on as well so
其他 的 事情怎么回事， 以及使
thanks for showing up today this is as I
感谢您今天显示出来 ，这是因为我
said last time these two lectures are
上次说这两个讲座都
not part of the course syllabus they're
不是课程大纲 他们 的一部分
not on the final exam they're more
没有期末考试他们更
looking to the future and in particular
展望未来，特别是
what I want to talk about today is some
我想今天 谈 一些
kind of studying I did over the past
样的学习我做了过去
year about how the electronics industry
一年如何电子行业
what we now call the semiconductor
我们现在所说的半导体
industry but it might be something
业内但它可能是
different in the future as new
未来随着新的 不同
technology comes along but what what
技术时，但什么什么
directions it's going to head and what
方向它会头什么
we'd be able to assume the kind of
我们希望能够 承担 的那种
progress that we've come to know and
我们已经认识到进步和
expect over the past several decades
预计在过去的几十年
so in particular and this is important
所以特别是，这 是非常重要的
for obviously for people involved in ECE
对于明显 对参与 ECE 人
but also for people involved in computer
也为人们参与计算机
science and software because the fact
科学和软件因为事实
that we have this massive collection of
我们对此有大量 收集
computers data centers powerful cell
电脑数据中心强大的 细胞
phones and things obviously the software
手机和 东西显然是软件
people are important to that but the
人到 ，但 重要
reality is it's the hardware base that
现实情况 是它的硬件基础，
makes it possible so it's really an
能够所以它是一个真正的
important thing even for software people
甚至重要的软件人
to have a fairly decent understanding of
有一个相当不错的 理解
how the actual systems work what their
实际的系统是如何工作的什么
technology is and what's it going to
技术是什么，就是它会
look like in the future so in particular
看起来像在 未来如此特别
we've been riding enjoying the benefits
我们一直享受 骑行 的好处
of what's commonly referred to as
一个什么样的通常 被称为
Moore's law and Gordon Moore is he still
摩尔定律和戈登·穆尔是他仍然
alive and was one of the earlier
活着，是较早的企业之一
pioneers in the semiconductor industry
在半导体 行业先锋
he worked for William Shockley who's one
他曾 在威廉·肖克利 谁的一个
of the inventors of the transistor and
晶体管 的发明人 及
set up there's a company called Shockley
设置 有 一个叫肖克利公司
semiconductor that Shockley set up in
半导体该肖克莱在设置
the Bay Area in Palo Alto in the late in
湾区的帕洛阿尔托的后期
the early nineteen know in the 1950s
早在20世纪知道20 世纪50年代
somewhere and then he
某个地方，然后他
and a group of them left because
和一群人离开，因为
Chalkley was such a jerk and found and
Chalkley是这样一个 混蛋，发现
found a home at an existing company
发现了一个家在现有的公司
called Fairchild that did things like
所谓飞兆半导体该做的事情一样
aviation electronics and set up
航空电子和设置
Fairchild Semiconductor and so that was
飞兆半导体等，这是
really the start of Silicon Valley from
真的是 从 硅谷开始
the silicon perspective actually they're
硅角度 实际上 他们是
using germanium at the time but what we
使用锗的时间，但我们什么
think of a Silicon Valley really got its
认为硅谷 真的得到了它
start there so he was the the the head
从那里开始，所以他是在头部
of the research part of Fairchild
飞兆半导体的研究部分
Semiconductor when he wrote an article
半导体时，他写了一篇文章
for a what's really just a trade press
对于什么是真的只是一个贸易新闻
magazine electronics magazine we
杂志电子杂志我们
wouldn't consider it a very important
会不会认为这是一个非常 重要的
publication these days but back then it
出版这些天，但当时它
had some fairly leading articles and so
有一些非常重要文章等
he wrote an article and this is in 1965
他写了一篇文章，这是在1965年
so almost exactly 50 years ago and what
所以几乎整整50年前，什么
he done was he just sort of evolved what
他做的是，他只是有点什么进化
his company was able to do in terms of
他的公司能够 在以下方面做
of building the very new of
的建设很新的
semiconductors and it was the very very
半导体和它是非常非常
early days of integrated circuits when
集成电路时的初期
you could put multiple transistors on a
你可以把在多个晶体管
single chip and what he recognized was
单芯片 和他认识是
there is sort of a curve of met that on
有几分的曲线满足上
this axis is how much does it cost to
该轴是多少的费用 是
per transistor to manufacture a system
每晶体管制造系统
and on the right hand side how many
并在 右手 边有多少
transistors there were on a single chip
晶体管有一个单个芯片上
and what he observed was through sort of
而 就是通过某种 他观察
a sweet spot and if you're to the left
甜蜜点，如果 你是向左
you're basically you're not putting
你 基本上你 不把
enough things on the chip and so you
芯片 等你 足够的东西
have too many chips and they cost a lot
有太多的筹码，他们花费了很多
to connect them together and you're not
将它们连接在一起，你是不是
making use of the technology and if you
利用该技术 ，如果你
go too far to the right then you're
走太远的权利，然后你
trying to squeeze more on that chip than
要挤更多的芯片比上
it was economically feasible at the time
它当时经济上可行
and what he also observe
什么，他也观察
was and this is 65 remember so he was
是，这是65记得让他
basically projecting from three years
基本上由三年突出
worth of data that that curve was
值得一数据是曲线的
dropping that and so the sweet spot was
该下降等等甜蜜 点是
shifting to telling you what's the
转向告诉你有什么
optimum number of devices to put on a
设备的最佳数目 穿上
single chip from like 20 here 250 there
从像20这里 有250 单芯片
too and then he projected out and said
太然后 他投射出来说
well gee by 1970 we should be able to
以及吉在1970年，我们应该能
get a thousand devices on a chip and
在一个芯片上 获得千元的设备 和
that was sort of just a prediction he
这是那种 只是一个预测，他
made and then that became known as
制造，然后被成为
Moore's law and that name was not made
摩尔定律 和 名字没有提出
up by Moore but by actually a professor
同比摩尔，但通过实际教授
at Caltech so what we now know of is
在加州理工学院所以我们现在知道的是
Moore's law was really started with this
摩尔定律是真的开始使用此
prediction and two things are worth
预测和两件事情是值得
noting one is it's a technology
注意一个是它是一个技术
prediction it's based on what this
预测它是基于这是什么
company and other companies were able to
公司和其他 公司能够
do but the other was an economic one it
这样做，但另一位是一个经济它
was saying if you want to make the best
是说，如果你想做出最好的
use of this technology and get the most
使用这种技术，并得到最
sort of electronics for your dollar then
电子排序为您的美元，然后
you should be following these principles
你应该遵循以下原则
so and that that combination is actually
因此和该组合 实际上 是
quite important so I went off and found
很重要的，所以我去了，发现
a Wikipedia page that lists a bunch of
维基百科页面，其中列出 了一堆
different chips for microprocessors and
微处理器不同的芯片和
other types of processors that has the
其它类型的处理器具有
both the chip area and how many
无论是芯片面积和多少
transistors who were on that and I
晶体管谁是对我
mapped it out so it starts the first
映射出来，所以它开始第一
microprocessor was called the 4004 made
微处理器被称为 作出 的 4004
by Intel in 1971 and up through here you
由英特尔于1971年，通过了你在这里
see that I sort of partitioned these
看到我有点划分这些
into different types of processors so a
成 不同类型的处理器的 一个这样
desktop processor would be like what
台式机处理器将像什么
you'd have in a PC and they sort of
你必须在一台PC，他们的排序
drove the industry for this middle part
推动了行业的这一中间环节
of the time embedded systems are chips
的时间嵌入式系统是芯片
that aren't designed to be computers
没有被设计成电脑
that you're using as computers but
您正在使用的电脑，但
they're inside of something for example
他们的东西，例如内
the earliest micro problem
最早的微型问题
the four thousand four was created by
四个一千四被创造
Intel to to run a calculate cop
英特尔运行 计算COP
calculator built by a Japanese company
计算器由日本 公司建造
they came to Intel and said could you
他们来到英特尔，说你能不能
make us some electronics to implement
让我们一些电子设备来实现
this and somebody within Intel I had the
在英特尔内部此，有人我有
inspiration to say well if we just
如果我们只是灵感，说好了
implement this as a microprocessor then
实现此微处理器然后
we can write the code to implement a
我们可以编写代码来实现
desktop calculator and it's what they
台式计算器，它是什么，他们
call 4-bit microprocessor so you're used
致电4位微处理器所以你使用
to 32 mentioned four so the word size is
至32 提到的 四个，字的大小是
four and how do you do that it's
四年你怎么做，它的
actually you have to think about how you
其实你要想想 如何
even do that but that's what it was a
即使这样做，但，这就是 它是一个
4-bit microprocessor so anyways embedded
4位微处理器，以便嵌入反正
systems sort of some of these were
其中一些的系统排序分别为
really a pre PC era and then these
一个真正的预PC时代 ，然后将这些
diamonds are ones that sort of drove the
钻石是那些那种开车
PC era and then the yellow are more
PC时代，那么黄更
recent graphic processor unit which are
最近图形处理器单元，其是
some of the biggest fastest chips out
一些最大最快的芯片的出
there the x's are ones that are really
有x是那些 真的
server class machines for example the
服务器级别的机器例如
shark machines and are designed to be
鲨鱼机被设计成
inside of a big computer room and down
一个大的机房内，下
here for example ones are actually for
例如这里的人实际上是对
cell phones but this is just this is not
手机但这只是这不是
a scientific sample it's just a one
科学的样品，它只是一个一个
through which I could find the
通过它我能找到的
appropriate data oh and you might ask
适当的数据哦，你可能会 问
why did you start in 1971 if this paper
你为什么要在1971年开始，如果本文
came out in 65 well back in 65 the
在65出来也早在65
technology is what they called bipolar
技术是他们所谓的双极
technology which is not a mental
技术是不是 一种 精神
condition here and the it's very
调理这里和它是非常
different
不同
so the first microprocessor and all the
所以第一微处理器和所有的
successor ones are done in a technology
继任者是 在 做 技术
called MOS which stands for metal oxide
称为MOS其代表金属氧化物
semiconductor which is in a very useful
半导体这是一个非常有用的
name but basically chips since the early
从早期的名字，但基本上筹码
seventies have dominantly been using
使用七十年代已经显性过
this technology and the current one is
该技术 与目前的一个是
called CMOS
所谓的CMOS
so anyways the interesting thing you'll
所以反正有趣的事情，你会
see here is on this log scale you'll see
在这里看到的是这个数刻度你会看到
that this doubling every two years has
这个每两年翻一番已
almost exactly matched what's happened
几乎完全 匹配发生了什么
so the gray line is if I just
所以灰线是，如果我只是
extrapolated from from 50 transistors in
从 在50个晶体管外推
1965 and predicted they would double
1965年和预测他们将增加一倍
every two years you get the gray line
每两年 你得到的灰线
and the black line is what I get running
而黑线是我所得到的 运行
a regression on this data and you'll see
对此数据 进行回归 ，你会看到
that their scopes are exactly the same
其范围是完全 一样的
and what that means is the doubling
而那意味着增加一倍
every two years is absolutely true and
每隔两年是绝对真实
the black line what it says is well
黑线它说什么是好
actually they in the early days they got
实际上，他们在创业初期，他们得到了
ahead of the curve somewhat so that the
领先的曲线有所 从而使
first microprocessor for example 4004
例如4004第一微处理器
had around well actually I have the
有大约还有其实我有
numbers actually add 1700 transistors so
数字实际添加1700倍的晶体管，这样
not too far off of what more addicted
不算太离谱的东西更加沉迷
for 1970 so anyways that's the point
1970年如此，反正这就是问题所在
it's an amazing thing this is held and
正是这种保持一个惊人的事情，
you might ask why was like Gordon Moore
你可能会问，为什么像戈登·穆尔
the the best forecaster of the future
未来的最好预报
ever to be able to nail this number so
以往任何时候都能够 敲定这多少让
precisely and also why do you call it a
恰恰也是为什么你叫它
law so there's two things going there's
法，使有两件事情去 那里的
a few things going on here first of all
几件事情会在 这里 首先是
this is not a law it's not a law of
这不是一个法律它不是一个法律
nature it's not a law of our country
自然这不是我们国家的法律
it's not a law of of anything it's just
它不是一个法律的任何东西，它只是
a statement that he made but also it's
声明说，他做了，而且它的
become a self-fulfilling aw meaning that
成为一个自我实现的AW含义
because Gordon Moore who is a very
因为戈登·穆尔谁是一个非常
prominent person at the time said this
突出的人 说，当时这
and said his company in that direction
并说他的公司在这个方向
and he then went on to found in tell by
他随后又 在告诉找到
the way he and and all of his colleagues
在路上，他和所有同事
and his sort of burgeoning business have
和 他那种 蓬勃发展的业务有
just been dedicated to the task of
只是一直致力于任务
making this a law so it was a prediction
这使其成为法律 ，使这是一个预测
but not in a sort of objective sense it
但不是一种客观意义上，它
was a prediction by somebody who then
是预测由某人谁再
motivated other people to fulfill it so
激励其他人实现它，
anyways it's pretty interesting that
反正这是很有趣的是 ，
just collect and if you can collect all
仅仅收取，如果你能收集所有
kinds of data and you'll find this this
类型的 数据 ，你会发现这本
doubling pretty much holds by the way in
加倍几乎保持在路上
general you should whenever you're
一般来说，你应该每当你
looking at a semi-log pot if you have a
看一个半对数锅，如果你有一个
straight line that's a sign of
直线的的标志
exponential growth so what does it
指数增长那么什么
really mean then it's hard for you to
真的是那么它是你很难
appreciate how much different the world
体会多少不同的世界
of computing is today than it was even
计算的是今天比它甚至
20 30 40 years ago so for example in
20 30 40 年前 如此，例如在
1976 if you had a lot of money in other
1976年，如果你有很多 钱 在其他
words your Los Alamos National
也就是说你的洛斯阿拉莫斯国家
Laboratory and you really wanted a big
实验室和你真的想要一个大
computer you could buy it by basically
计算机，你可以通过基本上买它
getting a hand-built machine from a
从得到一个手工打造的机
company called Cray headed by Seymour
一家名为克雷西摩为首
Cray who is one of the legendary people
克雷谁就是传说中的人物之一
in the world of computing at the time
在计算当时的世界
but this machine is you see all the
但是这 台机器是你看到 所有的
numbers for it are way off what even
它数字的路要走 ，甚至什么
I've got on my phone and what you have
我有我的电话，你有什么样的
on your phone to write in terms of
您的手机上来讲写
performance in terms of density this
这种 密度 方面 的 性能
thing weighed 5,000 kilograms and used
事情称重5000千克和使用
115 kilowatts where is now we have these
115千瓦哪里是我们现在有这些
ones that are powered by batteries and
由电池供电者和
fit near pockets and the other is
适合近口袋 ，另一个是
numbers that the whole life of the crane
数字， 起重机 的一生
this was considered an incredibly
这被认为是一个令人难以置信
successful supercomputer the first real
成功的超级计算机的第一个真正的
supercomputer in the whole lifetime they
超级计算机在整个生命周期，他们
manufactured 80 of them and as you know
他们制造的80，当你 知道
phones sell in the millions so it's
手机在百万卖那么它的
really very very different world we live
真的非常非常不同的世界，我们的生活
in because of of the progress of
在由于建设进度
integration and so again to put yourself
集成等再次把自己
back back in 65 what I can like I'll
背背65 我喜欢什么我就
date myself I was a young person at that
到目前为止，我自己， 我是一个年轻的人在该
time
时间
and for me the coolest thing to get was
而对我来说， 获得 最酷的事情 是
a portable transistor radio like this
便携式晶体管收音机这样
one that would play AM stations okay now
一个会玩 AM电台 现在没事了
today what young teenagers crave for is
今天的青少年的渴望是
the sort of waitest consumer product of
那种waitest消费品
a high-end funk so part of it is if you
高端 临阵脱逃 所以它的一部分是，如果你
look at this they even advertise this
看这他们甚至宣传这个
transistor radio had nine transistors on
晶体管收音机有九个晶体管上
it whereas the chip inside of a this is
它而内部的这种芯片 是
last year's the iPhone six had up has if
去年iPhone的6名患者已高达如果
you still have one a chip with two
你还有一个带有 两个 芯片
billion transistors on it and that's the
十亿个晶体管就可以了，这就是
main chip there's about eleven chips in
主芯片有大约十一芯片
an iPhone in a phone by the way that's
在电话的iPhone通过 这 方式
the main processor chip so that's really
主处理器芯片，这样真的
the the fundamental difference of why
为何根本区别
what you've got today is so different
你今天有如此 不同
than what you could get in 65
比 你能在65弄
so it's hard to even think about two
因此很难甚至认为约两
billion transistors and what that really
十亿个晶体管，什么真的
means so here's an analogy imagine a
意味着所以这里的一个 类比想象
transistor where the size of a grain of
晶体管，其中的晶粒的大小
sand they're actually a lot smaller than
沙他们其实比小了很多
that but just that's about the smallest
这只是这是关于最小
thing you can think of sort of picking
你能想到的排序采摘的东西
up and feeling then if you look at
起来，感觉那么如果你看看
here's this original four thousand four
这里是这个原四一千四
had 2,300 transistors I didn't have my
有2300个晶体管，我没有我的
numbers quite right
数字完全正确
so that's if you think in sand grains
所以这就是，如果你认为在沙粒
it's um actually I calculated this out
它 嗯其实我计算 了 这 一点
it's 170th of a teaspoon so just a very
这是第170 一茶匙的所以 只是很
very small pinch of sand is about 2,300
沙子非常小的夹点2300
grains of sand and nowadays if you think
沙粒与时下，如果你认为
of two billion transistors in in terms
在中关于两个十亿个晶体管
of sand that's about 200 pounds of sand
沙那约200磅 的沙子
so if you go to Home Depot and you buy a
所以，如果你去Home Depot和你买
bag of sand for your children's for
砂袋为您的 孩子对
somebody's a sandbox or whatever it's
某人的 沙箱或不管它是
about 50 pounds so about four four bags
约 50 磅 所以大约四四袋
of sand is 2 billion two billion grains
沙为2十亿 两个十亿粒
so that sort of where we are today we're
所以那种我们 今天的 情况 我们
at sort of a it's the same as if you
在排序的是 一样的 ，如果你
filled up big paint bucket three of them
填补了大油漆桶他们三个
sort of that level we're at so just to
那种级别的 我们在这样 只是为了
give you a sense where we are and so
给你一个感觉， 我们 是等
what I claim is and this isn't just my
我的主张是 ， 这 不只是我的
claim it's sort of self-evident that
声称 这是某种 不言而喻的是 的
there's a sort of virtuous cycle that
有一种良性循环的那
driven that drives the technology and
驱动驱动技术
the economics together so in particular
经济学在一起，特别是
the more things they can sell that they
更多的东西，他们 可以出售他们
have chips in them the more money that
有芯片他们更多的钱
gives for companies and more incentive
给企业 和更多的激励
that gives them to invest in research
这给了他们投资研究
and development to improve the
求发展，以改善
technology to buy it's a very expensive
技术买这是一个非常昂贵的
capital equipment to run a semiconductor
资本设备运行 半导体
fabrication facility and so that money
制造工厂，并让钱
comes from ultimately because they're
来自最终，因为 他们是
selling this stuff and because of that
卖 ，因为这 东西 ，
they're then able to improve the
他们就 能够改善
technology pack more transistors
技术包更多的晶体管
a chip make them run faster reduce the
芯片让他们跑得更快降低
power all those good things and then
电源所有这些美好的事物，然后
that's coupled with people who are good
多数民众赞成加上人谁是好的
at a product design and of course the
在产品设计过程中的
software designers as well to improve
软件设计以及改善
the product so that you want to buy more
让你想购买更多的产品
stuff right and that causes more sales
东东吧，并导致更多的销售
so this cycle is very important that if
所以这个周期 是非常重要的，如果
it weren't for that looping around then
它是不是为循环然后左右
these improvements wouldn't be happening
这些改进将不会 发生
so right now the semiconductor industry
所以，现在的半导体产业
is worldwide it's very much a
是全球 IT是 一种非常非常
international industry is about 300
国际产业约 300
billion dollars a year so it's pretty
每年十亿美元，因此是相当
big and so what does that meant well one
大，所以这意味着什么，搞好一个
is simply let's just take the example of
简直是让我们只采取的 例子
phones that the iPhone the first iPhone
手机， 在iPhone第一代iPhone
was on 2007 or so and there's been nine
是 在2007年左右，而且也已有9
generations of them including the most
他们的后代包括最
recent which isn't shown this picture
最近未示出 这个图象
and so more or less every year they come
所以 每年或多或少 他们来
out with a new phone and for example
了一个新的手机和例如
this phone I'm carrying around is one I
这款手机我随身携带一个我
bought this fall even though I had a
买了这个秋天，即使 我有一个
phone of from two years ago that was
从两年前 那 是手机
really okay but I was sufficiently
真的好吗 但我已经足够
motivated to shell out the money and now
主动地掏出钱 ，现在
it's not hidden in our plans anymore so
它不是 藏 在我们的计划了，所以
I know this actually cost me $750 but I
我知道这竟然 花了我$ 750，但我
and many of my friends and people around
和很多朋友和 周围 的人
the world did exactly that and created a
世界正是这样做 ，并创建了一个
huge pile of of cash that infused Apple
的巨额现金一堆苹果注入
and part of the reason Apple now is the
其中的原因苹果 的部分 现在是
largest company in the world in terms of
最大的公司在世界 上来讲
market capitalization so that cycle you
市值 让你循环
can see here you know better products
看到这里，你知道更好的产品
more sales you you see that happening
更多的销售，你看到这种情况发生
all the time but underneath it all
所有的 时间，但下面这一切
what's driving that then is the ability
是什么力量推动这则是一种 能力
to improve these products so you've
所以，你要提高这些产品
probably heard the other kind of stuff
可能听说过其他类似的东西
people are talking about is artificial
人们都在谈论 是人为
intelligence and we'll it basically
情报，我们将它 基本上
eliminate all your jobs and the famous
消除所有作业 和著名
sort of person behind that it's a guy
何许人身后， 这是一个男人
named Ray Kurzweil
命名雷·库尔宗韦尔
um and so he proposed this idea they
嗯，所以他提出了这个想法 ，他们
called a singularity which is the the
称为奇点，其是在
day
天
this is I'll just describe it to you can
这是我就形容它给你可以
tell I'm skeptic on this the day that
告诉 我在这一天怀疑论者认为
computers become more powerful than
计算机变得更为强大
humans actually that he's not the one
其实人类，他是不是一个
who invented that term then it's all of
谁发明了这个词那么它的所有的
a sudden going to create this massive
突然要创造这个巨大的
switchover where the computers are going
切换计算机所在打算
to get smarter by teaching themselves to
自己教学得到更聪明
be smarter and sort off into infinity of
更聪明和排序断成 无限
making humans obsolete that's the idea
使人类过时这想法
of the singularity and part of the
的 奇异 和部分
argument behind this is basically from
这 背后的说法 基本上是从
moore's law
摩尔定律
so what Crick's well did in this picture
还等什么克里克 以及在这张照片做
and it actually started with some work
它 实际上开始 与一些工作
by a person who used to be the robotics
通过谁曾经是机器人的人
Institute here was he plotted based on
这里研究所为他绘制的基础上
this his measure was calculations per
这他的措施是每计算
second per thousand dollars so how much
第二每千元的多少
computation could you buy for a thousand
计算你能买一千年
dollars and he started back in 1900 with
美元，他在 1900年 开始回来 了
mechanical adding machines and stuff
机械加法机和东西
like that and added these plots you see
这样并加入这些情节你看
this was around 2000 and somehow this is
这是在2000年左右，不知何故，这是
an article of amazing a potting he
惊人的 灌封 的文章中，他
figured that this wasn't even a straight
想通这甚至不是一条直线
line it was an upward curve so an upward
线，这是一个向上 弯曲，从而向上
curve on a semi-log paper is more than
在半对数纸上曲线超过
exponential it's like e to the x squared
指数是像电子，以方在x
or something like that right
或类似的东西 的权利
so but anyways based on that projection
所以，不管它了基于该投影
and based on some notion of the relative
而基于相对的概念，一些
power of human versus Mouse versus
人类与 老鼠 与电源
insect brains he came out with this
昆虫的大脑，他想出了这个
projection that in 2030 roughly
投影，在2030大致
computers would become smarter than
计算机将变得比聪明
humans and if you just keep that on Kim
人类，如果你只是保持上 金
eight computers would become smarter
八台计算机 将变得更聪明
than all humans combined so that we can
不是所有的人结合起来， 使我们能
talk about this projection and I'm sure
谈论这个投影和我敢肯定
you guys do at times too
你们有时候做的太
but my point of it is this argument it's
但我对它的一点是这种说法很
fundamentally a Moore's Law argument
本质上是一个摩尔定律 说法
right that the argument is basically as
正确的说法基本上是作为
computational power increases because of
由于计算能力的增加
this continuing progress of technology
技术 的这种持续进步
it's inevitable that because humans
这是不可避免 的，因为人类
aren't really getting smarter much of a
是不是真的变聪明了很多的
very fast rate that it's inevitable that
速度非常快 ，这是不可避免 的，
computers will become smarter than
计算机将变得比聪明
humans said Souter the argument but it's
人说，苏特的说法 ，但它的
very much based on this assumption that
很多 基于 这种假设，
computer technology is going to continue
计算机技术将继续
to progress at an exponential pace
以指数级的速度 取得进展
so let's now imagine and this is
现在让我们想象一下，这是
something that you know you could be
你知道你可以的东西
thinking about is is what will this mean
想的是什么，这将意味着
50 years from now
50年 后
so if Moore's law looks back over the
因此，如果摩尔定律 会回头
past 50 years now let's look forward for
过去50年，现在让我们期待 的
another 50 years and see what that would
50 年，看看那会
mean and what would possibly be so one
意味着什么将可能是这样一个
claim I'll make is that whatever is the
要求我要让是， 无论是
most important thing it will be
最重要的是这将是
something that is in the hands of
东西是 在手中
everyone or is even more ubiquitous than
大家或者 甚至 比 更 无处不在
there are humans on the planet right in
有人类在这个星球就在上
other words that what I claim is the
这就是我要求的是换句话说
thing that will be the most important
件事， 这将是最重要的
technology wise will be what's the
技术 明智的将是什么的
largest volume product so I'm not sure
体积最大的产品，所以我不知道
what that will be in 2065 it certainly
什么，这将是2065它肯定
will not be called a cell phone it will
不会被调用手机它会
look like what we think is a phone after
是什么样子，我们认为 这是一个电话后，
all of all the things people own cell
所有的一切东西的人自己的细胞
phones for what do you use it for the
手机为你怎么 用它作
least making calls right Reese for me so
至少酝酿 了我的 要求权 里斯如此
who knows what it will be but I claim
谁知道这将是 ，但我要求什么
that and this is a key part of this
这一点，这是这方面的一个重要组成部分
argument that I claim it's got to be a
我要求它有 一个参数 是一个
portable low power system so it has to
便携式低功耗的系统，所以它必须
be powerful computation but has to be
是强大的计算 ，但 必须是
physically small and it can't draw much
身体小，它不能得出太多
power
功率
and that will be and so it might be you
这将是，所以它可能是你
know the Internet of Things where
知道东西放在互联网
everything is networked together and
一切都联网在一起，
there's computer chips or various chips
有计算机芯片或各种芯片
and everything that those kind of things
和一切这种事情
would also have the kind of volumes
也有那种卷
needed to drive the market forward so
需要推动市场 向前发展，从而
based on that sort of let's make that
基于那种让我们做的是
one part of assumption is whatever
假设一个部分是什么
drives the future it's going to be
驱动未来这将是
something that is portable low power and
东西是便携式 低 功耗和
low cost you know consumer grade or
低成本你知道消费级或
something that you can afford to just
的东西，你 能负担得起，只是
sprinkle across the whole planet or
在整个星球上洒或
across the whole galaxy if we're beyond
在整个银河系 ，如果我们超越
Earth at that point so that means for
地球在这一点上，使 装置
example that it's not going to be a
例如，它的不会是一个
quantum computer right
量子计算机 的权利
quantum cholesterol to make
量子胆固醇，使
breakthroughs in superconducting
在 超导 突破
something that you have to cool down to
你必须冷静下来的东西
near absolute zero requires a big room a
接近绝对零度 ，需要一个大房间
lot of equipment and a lot of power and
很多的设备和大量 的电力和
a lot of things to manage it so you're
很多事情来管理 它，所以你是
not going to carry that around in your
不打算去了随身携带 您的
pocket I can promise you that so all the
口袋，我可以向你保证，因此，所有 的
people talking about a quantum computer
人们谈论 量子计算机
well we can just rule that out that's
好我们就可以排除这种可能性这是
not going to be the the most important
不会是最重要的
thing out there but it and it also you
在那里的事情，但它同时也你
know if you could imagine building this
知道你是否 能 想象这个建筑
huge machine that occupies many acres of
占据多少亩的庞大机
buildings that's not going to be the
这不会是建筑
most exciting thing out there because
最令人兴奋的事情了那里，因为
it's it there's not enough of those to
这是它有没有足够的那些的
sort of drive the market and without
排序的推动市场，没有
that market there won't be in the
这个市场不会有在
investment in the technology so it has
投资于技术，因此它具有
to be inexpensive and what if we think
是价格低廉，如果我们认为
of it in computer science terms big
在计算机科学术语大呢
o-notation it can't be you know the cost
邻符号不能是你认识的成本
to produce these things can't be very
产生这些 事情不能很
much so for example the chip that's in
竟有如此例如这是在芯片
the cell phone that Apple AAA costs
手机 ，苹果 AAA成本
somewhere between ten and twenty dollars
介于十二十 元
for Apple to procure that from its
苹果以促使其
suppliers which are in Taiwan and in
供应商，其在台湾和
Korea so they're not very expensive
韩国所以他们不是很昂贵
that said it need not be anything based
它不需要任何 基础说
on the technology we use today as I
在技术上我们 今天 使用 的我
mentioned currently things are CMOS and
目前提到的事情是CMOS和
it's been some kind of moss MOS since
它已经某种苔藓 MOS 自
the 1970s so for a long time but
20世纪70年代等了很长时间，但
probably won't continue to be that way
可能不会继续这样
at least not in the way we know it and
至少不是 在路上，我们 知道它 ，
these various other ideas people have
这些不同的其他想法的人有
had for future computer technology that
有 对未来的计算机技术 ，
beyond this and some of it's being
超出这一范围， 它的一些是
worked on here at CMU and I won't
曾在这里CMU， 我不会
predict what those could be but they
预测这些可能 是什么，但他们
have to have these characteristics has
必须有 这些特点 有
to be inexpensive has being low-power
是便宜的 具有为低功耗
has to be scalable so that's my one
具有可扩展性，这样是我的一个
assumption then I'm going to add is
假设然后我要补充的是
whatever it is we're going to want a lot
不管它是什么，我们会想 很多
of them a lot of transistors or devices
他们中的 很多 晶体管或设备
of some sort so what does that mean if
某种所以这是什么意思，如果
we project that out in terms of how many
我们预计 出多少的条款
devices are on a chip not not how many
设备是在一个芯片上 没有没有多少
transistors four devices so one great
晶体管四个设备这样一个巨大
thing about semi-log pots is you can
约半对数盆的事情是，你可以
just extrapolate to your heart's content
只是推断 你的心脏的内容
so if we just run those two curves that
所以，如果我们只是运行这两个曲线，即
I showed you before out you get
我 之前 表现出你 出去你
somewhere we'll just you know pick a
地方我们就知道你挑
number that sort of roughly in the
数排序 大致在
middle of those two projections of 10 to
的10至这两个凸起的中间
the 17th so 10 to the 17th things
17日，因此将10至17件事
devices in a single integrated system of
在一个单一 的 集成系统中的设备
some kind and that would be what we'd be
某种这 将是我们会是什么
looking at so how big is 10 to the 17th
看着这么多大10至17
well if we go back to our sand analogy
那么，如果我们回到 我们的沙比喻
this is a picture I found on the
这是一个图片我就发现
internet of some young man in Brazil on
一些年轻人在巴西互联网
a beach making a scale model of the
一个海滩上做的一个比例模型
Empire State Building out of sand so my
帝国大厦明砂的，所以我的
estimate is this is roughly something
估计是这大致是 什么
like 3 billion grains of sand in that
就像在沙三十亿粒
thing I didn't count them I have didn't
事我没指望他们我还没有
yet but so so think in terms so
不过也因此这么认为的条款，以便
something you know roughly the same
您知道的东西大致相同
scale I showed you of those 4 bags of
规模我给你的那些 4袋
sand from Home Depot something that's
从家得宝 的东西，是沙
roughly comparable
大致相当于
what we'd get on a chip today if if
我们会在一个芯片上的今天得到，如果如果
transistors were the size of a grain of
晶体管分别的晶粒的大小
sand so what does 10 to the 17th mean
沙等什么 呢10至17的平均
well if you actually built a sand model
还有，如果你真的建立了一个沙模型
of the Empire State Building that
帝国大厦的那
one-to-one scale right then that's a
一到一个合适的规模那么这是一个
million cubic meters and then if you
万立方米，然后如果你
made two replicas of that then and some
由这则有的两个副本
of those three together then you'd get
这三个在一起， 那么你会得到
about 10 to the 17th grains of sand so
约10至砂17粒这样
of course we're assuming this is going
当然， 我们假定这是怎么回事
to be something a lot more than a grain
比一粒的东西多 了很多
of sand but just to give you a sense of
沙子，但只是给你的感觉
scale of how big a change that would be
有多大变化 的规模，这将 是
going from a few billion to 10 to the
从数 十亿要10到
17th is a pretty big jump in terms of
17 来讲是一个相当大的跳跃
how many devices are involved so let's
多少设备 参与让我们
figure out how could we make things you
搞清楚我们如何能够让你的事情
know let's just say well let's just try
知道让我们只 说好 ，让我们只是 尝试
running the numbers and seeing what
运行数字 和看到的
would happen if we just took our current
如果我们 只是把我们目前 会发生
technology which is more or less what
技术，是多了还是少了什么
we've been using since 1970 of putting a
我们一直在使用自1970年以来的一个推杆
lot of transistors on a single chip
很多晶体管的单芯片上
actually I happen to bring some toys
其实我正好带一些玩具
with me today this is a wafer so this is
今天我来说这是 一个晶片上，这是
what comes through a fabrication plant
什么来通过一个制造工厂
and it's got typically about 700
并且它有一般约700
individuals whether they called I on
个人是否 他们叫我上
them but then they slice up and they put
他们，但那么他们切片， 并把它们
in packages so these are some old
在包所以这些都是一些老
packages but now on your phone or your
包中，而是你的手机或上
laptops whose packaging in there so they
笔记本电脑 ，其包装在里面，使他们
package the the chips inside of there so
打包的有这么内的芯片
typically then this is the current size
然后通常是这样的电流的大小
that a company manufactures a diet at 30
一个公司生产的30节食
centimeters so about 1 foot in diameter
因此厘米约1英尺直径
and you get about 700 chips on it to
你得到 它 的大约700 芯片
typically around one square centimeter
通常约为1平方厘米
so let's just say well let's just take
所以让我们只说好 ，让我们只 取
that technology which over the years
这项技术，多年来
these these die of these chips have
这些死这些这些芯片具有
gotten the wafers have gotten bigger the
得到晶圆已经变得更大了
die
死
gotten a little bit bigger and we've
变得有点大了，我们拿
also been able to make much finer
还能够进行更精细
geometries on these chips so let's sort
这些芯片的几何形状让我们整理
of see how we've got this over history
的看到我们是如何 得到这个历史上
and what the projections of that would
什么的，突起会
mean and what the data show is that the
意味着什么数据显示的是，
way we've achieved is sort of doubling
我们已经取得的方式是那种加倍
every two years in how many transistors
每两年在多少晶体管
were on a chip is one the trips have
是在一个芯片上是一个车次有
gotten bigger they've doubled in size
变得更大了，他们已经大一倍
the rate of once every ten years and
每 10年 一次 的速度 和
also the geometries have gotten finer
也有几何形状变得更细
that we've they've doubled in size or
我们已经他们已经大一倍或
halved in size where the density we can
在尺寸减半其中密度 ，我们可以
get as a result has gone by a factor to
得到的 结果已经由一个因素
every about four times in ten years and
在每十年约四次
so you sum those up you get five
所以你总结了那些你送五
doublings every ten years and that's how
倍增每隔十年 ，这就是如何
you get Moore's law so in particular if
你摩尔定律所以特别是如果
you look at the earliest chip the four
你看看最早的芯片四
thousand four was about twelve square
一千四是约十二万
millimeters so that it's pretty small
毫米，使得它非常小
and a modern chip is typically around a
和一个现代化的芯片通常是围绕着
square centimeter so and this is
平方厘米 左右，这 是
actually to scale to a dime there are
实际上扩展到一毛钱有
some bigger chips out there and they're
一些较大的筹码在那里，他们是
not really blue they just did this to
没有真正的蓝色，他们只是做了这
make it look nice but IBM for example
使它 看起来不错，但IBM例如
makes a server where the chip size is
使一个服务器，其中芯片尺寸
almost ten times larger than than this
不是比这个更大的十倍
processor so you can get some pretty big
处理器让你可以得到一些相当大的
dye out there but those are typically
染料在那里，但那些通常
only and also some GPUs can be pretty
只是，也有一些图形处理器可以很
big dot so those are used either in
大圆点所以那些使用，也可以在
servers or in places where they're
在地方，他们的服务器或
pretty specialized for more portable
相当专业的更便携
battery-powered things you have to go
你必须去电池供电的事
with smaller chips so this is the data
用更小的芯片，所以这是该数据
showing the area for these different
示出了用于这些不同的区域
micro processors for time and you can
微型处理器 的 时间，你可以
see that you're kind of all over the map
看你是那种所有在地图上
so it's a little risky to do any kind of
所以这是一个 有点冒险做任何形式的
extrapolation here but this is where I
外推在这里，但这个是我
got the number that it's doubled roughly
得到了它的大约翻了一番数
every ten
每十
the area of the chip so if we project
该芯片的面积，所以如果我们的项目
that out then then we get something of
说出来，然后再我们得到的东西
173 square centimeters so those of you
173平方厘米所以那些你
metrically challenge that number
度量上挑战这个数字
probably doesn't mean much to you but
可能并不意味着什么 给你，但
just to give you a sense like if I just
只是给你的感觉就像 如果 我只是
extrapolated then by the Year 2065 I
在2065年我然后外推
should be up to the Apple model a 59
应达苹果模式 一59
because right today's a 6s and so
因为今天的权利是一个6S等
anyways and it will as we said 10 to the
反正，它会为我们说10到
17 transistors that will be 173 square
17个晶体管 ，这将 是173平方
centimeters the problem with that is
厘米与问题
it's actually bigger than a dollar bill
它实际上比一美元的钞票 更大
it's about two dollar bills in size 173
这是大约 两美钞尺寸173
square centimeters and you're not going
平方厘米，你不会
to fit that in your pocket
适合在你的口袋里
notice you have really big pocket so
注意到你有 真正的大口袋等等
that is not the way things are going to
这不是事情的 进展的 方式
work we can't just keep scaling up area
工作中，我们不能只是一味地扩大面积
and expect that to happen
并希望这样的事情发生
well the other factor which is we showed
还有这是其他因素，我们表现
is more critical as things have gotten
更为关键的事情变得
smaller and so the way I'll I'll measure
小，所以 这样我会，我会衡量
that is I'll take this measure I call L
这是我要这个措施我叫大号
the linear metric of of chip density
的芯片密度的线性度量
I'll say the area of that chip divided
我会说，芯片 的面积 除以
by the number of transistors and so one
通过晶体管 的数量，因此一个
way to think about it is if the
考虑一种理解是，如果
transistors are spread in a sort of
晶体管散布在几分
uniform grid across a chip then their
由于芯片均匀网格然后他们
spacing would be this number L of course
间隔将是当然这个数目L
they're not there they're denser in some
他们是不是有他们在一些更密集
places and more spread out and others
地方和更加分散和其他
but sort of if you think of this as a
但那种，如果你认为这 是一个
way to look overall how close we packed
方式整体看我们 是如何 紧密 堆积
our transistors to each other and this
我们的晶体管到对方，这
is the curve you get from our existing
是你从我们现有的得到曲线
set of processors and you see this one
处理器组 ，你看这一个
really is a pretty strong trend of
真的 是一个非常强大的趋势
getting a finer and finer geometries
得到一个越来越精细的几何
over time
随着时间的推移
and it's so the linear scale it drops by
它是如此降至由 线性刻度
a factor of two every five years but if
二每五年但如果一个因素
you think about the number of things the
你想想 事情 的数量
density therefore goes by a factor of
因此密度的因数变为
four every five years and so that or
4每五年使或
equivalently I've gotten twice as many
等效我已经得到了两倍多
transistors in a given area every two
在给定 面积 的晶体管 每两年
and a half years
年半
and we can see that again in practice
我们可以在实践中 再次看到，
that if you measure out for the Intel
如果你测出的英特尔
4004 it comes out to 72,000 nanometers
4004它出来72,000纳米
10 to the ninth meters is this measure
10第九米 ，这一措施
and where's EPEL a 8 is 211 nanometers
哪来 一个 EPEL 8是211个纳米
so those you know about chip technology
所以那些你知道芯片技术
might know that the AAA was manufactured
可能知道AAA 制造
with what's called a 22 nanometer
用什么叫做22纳米
process so when they measure when you
处理所以当他们衡量你的时候
hear people talking about a process you
听到人们在谈论的过程你
know the actual fabrication process and
知道实际的制造工艺和
they give a number of nowadays and
他们给的时下数，
nanometers what I mean it's a sort of
纳米是什么我的意思是几分
closest spacing you can make two wires
最接近的间距可以让两条线
on a chip sort of finest geometry there
芯片之类的最好的几何形状上有
but this measure L is bigger because it
但这一措施L是更大的，因为它
accounts for not just out what you how
占不只是什么你如何
closely you can pack wires but all the
紧紧可以 包线，但所有的
other stuff you have to put transistors
其他的东西 ，你必须把晶体管
there you have to route power and ground
你有路由的电源和地
and signal wires to them and they have
线和信号线他们，他们有
to be isolated from each other so this
从彼此分离这
is actually a more useful measure of of
实际上是更有益的措施
the effect of spacing on a chip um so
间距的芯片庵等的影响
just to again if you're not so familiar
只是再次，如果你不那么熟悉
with this kind of geometry let's just
用这种几何形状 让我们只
give you some idea of it so this range
给你它的 一些想法 所以这个范围
in nanometers then between a thousand
在1,000至5,000纳米然后
and a million then is sort of something
一百万，然后是类的东西
smaller than a millimeter right a
超过一毫米小权
million nanometers is a millimeter so a
百万纳米是一毫米所以
thousand nanometers is a micron or a
千个纳米是一微米 或
micrometer and so this range which is
千分尺，因此该范围是
where some any conductor processing was
其中一些任何导体加工是
up till ten years ago you'd call it the
截至十年前 你会称它为
submillimetre range and in this it's in
亚毫米波范围 ，并在此它在
the sub micrometer range so just to give
亚微米范围，只是给
you some sense of what those scales mean
你的 那些什么意思规模 从某种意义上说
and I'll point out that it's pretty
我会指出，这是很
incredible to talk about something over
令人难以置信的谈了
six orders of magnitude in scale right
规模右六个数量级
that's in the physical world six orders
这是在物理世界六个数量
of magnitude is a law
幅度是有规律的
so again if you look at here's some
如此反复，如果你看一下 这里的一些
examples of things of how big is a
是多大的事情例子
micrometer often called a micron so you
千分尺通常被称为微米，所以你
know things that the are almost visible
知道的事情是，几乎可见
at this scale a human cell how thick a
在这个尺度 人体细胞有多厚
piece of plastic saran wrap is how thick
片塑料保鲜膜的是如何厚
a a strand of spider silk is gives you
蜘蛛丝的链是 给你
some rough number and so this Intel chip
一些粗略的数字，因此这Intel芯片的
from the seventies was somewhere in that
从七十年代在某处
range and now if we look somewhere
范围现在如果我们在其他 地方看
between a nanometer and a mic micrometer
一纳米和一个麦克风微米之间
and again this is a log pot or so these
而这同样是一个日志锅或使这些
things go pretty fast so for example all
事情非常快 ，所以例如 所有
a visible light is in this range between
可见光是在这个范围 之间
400 and 700 nanometers and the spacing
400个700纳米， 并且 间隔
of transistors on an Apple chip are
苹果芯片上的晶体管是
therefore closer than then the
因此比则越接近
wavelength of visible light by the way
可见光的波长的方式
which makes for kind of a challenge for
这使得样的挑战为
manufacturing something like how thick
制造类似有多厚
is a cell membrane or how what's the
是细胞膜或如何有什么
diameter of a strand of DNA are down in
DNA链的直径是在向下
just a few nanometer range what they
短短纳米范围内他们
call carbon Namek nanotubes which people
叫碳那美克星纳米管人
predict will be possibly a successor to
预计将成为可能的继任者
transistors their diameter not their
晶体管的直径不自己
length is one nanometer so those are
长度为一个纳米所以这些都是
pretty small when you're getting down
非常小，当你 越来越 下降
here and nowadays modern processes
这里如今现代化进程
they're trying to create features down
他们正试图打造特色下来
in this range of 14 nanometers example
在此范围内14个纳米示例的
okay but we can do our plot and if you
不错，但我们可以做我们的剧情，如果你
just project out you'll get down to this
只是伸出你会得到下降到本
linear spacing of 230 Pico meters in 50
在50的230微微米的线性间隔
years so what does that mean how big is
年，所以这是什么意思有多大
a Pico meter
微微米
well Pico meter is really small in fact
以及微微米的其实是非常小
if you look at the spacing between two
如果你看一下两者之间的间距
atoms in a silicon crystal they're about
在硅晶体他们即将原子
half of a nanometer
纳米一半
and if you look at the spacing between
如果你看看之间的间距
the two atoms in a hydrogen molecule
在氢 分子中的两个原子
there are 74 picometers so what the main
有74 皮米有啥主
thing to realize is this ain't going to
认识到的是 ，这是不打算
happen there is absolutely no way that
碰巧是绝对 没有办法，
we'll be able to create systems where
我们将 能够创建系统中
things are spaced only 230 Miko meters
事情的间距只有230 米 的巫女
apart right because presumably whatever
除了正确的，因为大概什么
we build is going to be bigger than a
我们打造的是会比更大
hydrogen atom or molecule so or you know
氢原子或分子 ，从而也知道
so this really is not in the range of
所以这 真的不是在范围内
physically possible and that's one of
物理可能的 ， 而且是一
the annoying things that physics has
恼人的事情，物理学
sort of gotten in the way of progress
排序得到在我们前进的道路
recently so in particular you know could
最近这样特别，你知道能
we imagine then let's just suppose we'll
然后我们想象我们只是想我们将
allow a chip we'll say let's go to chip
让我们先说芯片让我们去凑钱
be as big as 400 square millimetres just
是一样大的400 平方毫米刚
about twice as big on a side as the
约两倍大的一侧为
current chip current standard chip that
目前芯片目前标准芯片
would still require this spacing metric
仍然需要这种间隔指标
of 63 Pico meters in this isn't right
在这63微微米 是不正确的
yeah
是啊
because I'm not allowed to make chips to
因为我不能 做筹码
the size of $2 bills
$ 2张钞票大小
so it requires even finer spacing here
所以它需要更加精细间距这里
and we saw that's just 63 Pico meters is
我们看到，这只是63微微米，
actually closer than the two atoms in a
实际上比在两个原子更接近
hydrogen molecule the two nuclei in a
氢分子 在两个核
hydrogen molecule
氢 分子
so the answer is no this isn't going to
所以答案是否定的，这是不打算
happen this just playing is not possible
这 发生 只 打是不可能的
at least not you know so we have to back
至少 你不知道 ，所以我们需要备份
off and say well what's our defect our
关闭，说好什么是我们的缺陷我们
thinking one is to assume that we're
想一个是认为我们是
going to just take this current
打算自己使用这个电流
technology of two-dimensional things and
二维物联网 技术 和
just shrink it and one reason we look at
只是缩水了个中缘由，我们来看看
that way because that's exactly what's
这样，因为这正是 什么
happened over the past 50 years but we
发生在过去的50年，但我们
have three dimensions in this world and
在这个世界上三个维度和
so maybe there's some prospect there so
所以也许有一些前景有这么
let's say instead okay let's imagine a
比方说，而不是没关系，让我们想象
little brick of stuff and I'll just make
东西砖少，我只会让
up some numbers I'll say 2 centimeters
一些数字我会说2厘米
on a side and 5 millimeters high it's
上侧至5毫米高 是
almost exactly the same shape and volume
几乎完全一样的形状和体积
as a stack of five nickels and so and
如五个镍等的叠层和
now let's just imagine okay how are we
现在让我们来试想一下 ， 还好 是怎样的
going to integrate a bunch of things
要整合 一堆 东西
well presumably we're going to build it
以及想必我们要构建它
out of layers and so let's just assume
出层，所以我们只是 假设
that there's about a hundred thousand
有是 关于一个十万
layers worth of stuff and those are what
层价值的东西，那些是什么
I'll call logical layers meaning that
我会打电话给逻辑层意思是
they'll be about a million physical
他们将一百万个物理
layers because we have to have wires and
层，因为我们必须有电线和
these whatever we're building will be
这些无论我们正在建设将是
just these totally flat things nowadays
只是这些完全平坦的东西现在
there's a modern chip has more like 20
有一个现代化的芯片具有更喜欢20
physical layers on it so but the point
它的物理层 左右，但点
is that we'll have to have about a
是， 我们必须有 一个左右
million physical layers worth of stuff
万美元的东西的物理层
to get a hundred thousand logical layers
获得十万逻辑层
but that would allow us a spacing on the
但是，使我们对一个间距
linear spacing of about 20 nanometers so
约20纳米的线性间距，以便
20 nanometers is a lot better than a 63
20个纳米比 63 好多了
picometers right if we go back 20
皮米正确的，如果我们 回到20
nanometers is up in here so it's really
纳米达在这里，所以它真的
really small but it's not
真的很小，但它不是
it's not beyond a physical possibility
它无法超越物理可能性
which is put it that way so you could
这 是这样说的 话，所以你 能
imagine some technology that would give
想象一些技术， 这将使
you that so at least at some level it
你， 所以至少在 一定程度上它
it's vaguely you know it's aggressive
这是隐约 你知道它的 侵略性
but but possible to imagine in 50 years
但却有可能在50年内想象
be able to manufacture in a shape like
能够制造在一个形状像
that something with 10 to the 17th
的 东西 与10至17
devices but there's a few problems one
设备，但有几个问题之一
is actually the manufacturing how we do
实际上是制造，我们怎么办
actually do this is no small thing
真正做到这一点是不小的事情
another I'll talk about some is how do
另外，我会讲一些是怎么做的
we do this and not spend a whole lot and
我们这样做，而不是整体上投入很大，并
exorbitant amount of money doing it and
这样做的金钱数额过高和
the other is a huge huge problem of
另一种是一个巨大的大 问题
power consumption how can we actually
功耗岂能实际
have a system that complicated and keep
有一个系统，复杂的，并保持
it at the limited energy level we have
它在我们有限的能量水平
available so let me go into that some
可用，以便让 我去到一些
more so just is a sort of tutorial the
更何况仅仅是一种教程的
way these chips are made and part of the
这样这些芯片制成， 部分
reason they're so cheap is it's sort of
之所以他们这么便宜是它的排序
a photo process meaning that every step
光学处理，这意味着每一步
of the way is done by putting a some
的方式是通过将一个做一些
kind of material down and exposing it to
一种材料下来 ，并将其暴露 于
a light a laser light and then that this
一个光的激光光，然后，该
material that you've put down is
你已经放下 材料
light-sensitive and so there's a mask
对光敏感，所以有一个面具
that defines how things should be
定义的东西应该如何
patterned and the white only hits where
图案和白色 仅命中其中
the mask is allows it to and that's how
面膜是它允许，这就是如何
you get different shapes and things and
你会得到不同的 形状和事情，
you can either add material or you can
您可以添加材料，或者你 可以
remove material by these masking steps
由这些掩蔽步骤去除材料
so nowadays the modern chip takes about
所以时下现代芯片约需
60 of these steps we're involving a mask
这些步骤 60 我们涉及口罩
and some type of either depositing
和某种类型的任一沉积的
something or removing something or
东西或删除一些 或
shining light on it or a beam of ions or
上它的光辉光或离子束或
some other process step to do it so it's
其他一些工艺步骤做，所以它的
very complicated than the technology is
很复杂的比技术
quite remarkable but what you could say
相当显着，但你能说什么
is that the even though there's a couple
是 ， 即使有一对夫妇
billion transit
十亿过境
she's on a chip it still is a constant
她是一个芯片上，它仍然是一个常数
time process some fixed number of steps
时间过程中的一些固定 的步 数
and it's done and Beach successive
并且，它的完成和海滩连续
generation maybe the number of masking
一代也许掩蔽的数量
steps has increased a little bit over
步骤增加 了 一 点点
time but roughly speaking it's always a
时间，但大致说来，它总是一个
constant time operation and it turns out
固定时间的操作和原来
that the bottleneck in this and the
在这个和瓶颈
performance one is actually this
表现一个其实这是
photolithography exposing the chip the
光刻曝光的芯片的
the wafer using a mask and the way
使用掩模和路晶片
that's done nowadays is a machine called
多数民众赞成 现在做的 是一个叫机
a stepper that basically is used to scan
基本上用于扫描步进
over the wafer and expose with a laser
在晶片 和暴露用激光
sort of flashing as it goes to expose
有点闪烁，因为它去揭露
the wafer to this mask and so current
所述晶片，以该掩模 等电流
day that's done it up on a size of about
一天这样做了它的大小约为
eight hundred nine hundred square
809百平方公里
millimeters so you know about this
毫米，而你知道这个
bigger size how much they can expose at
更大的尺寸多少，他们可以在暴露
a time and the fastest steppers out
一时间，最快的步进出来
there can do a whole way for in eighteen
可有十八了做一个整体的方式
seconds which is pretty good if you
秒，这是你不错
think of waving over this whole area
想挥舞在 这个整个区域 的
flashing and exposing it with extremely
闪烁，具有极高暴露它
high resolution and very high alignment
高分辨率和非常高的定位
of reliability so but that's sort of the
可靠性因此但这是排序的
thing that sort of limits how many chips
东西之 类的限制多少筹码
you can run through a fabrication
您可以通过制造运行
facility per day is this stepper and the
每天设施是这个步进 和
stepper is the most expensive piece of
步进是最昂贵的片的
machinery in the building so you don't
机械在建筑让你不
want to buy a whole lot of them so
想要买一大堆人如此
that's sort of my point is that
这就是那种我 点 的 是，
lithography is the expensive thing so
光刻是昂贵的东西，所以
every layer we have to do if we have to
做我们每次有层如果 我们有
expose it using this technique is
其暴露在使用这种技术是
expensive and so there's no way you
昂贵的，所以也没有办法，你
could do a million layer system using
可以用做一个百万层系统
photo lithography and keep the expense
光刻 并保持费用
down to the range where it would be
到的范围内哪里会
something you or I would would be able
是你还是我会就 能够
to afford
负担
as a consumer device as I said a modern
作为消费设备如我所说的现代化
chip is somewhere between 10 and 20
芯片是10和20之间的某处
dollars so we're not talking a lot of
美元因此，我们说 的 不是 很多
money like well if you increase that
钱想好，如果你增加
cost by a hundred then people aren't
由一百那么成本人不
going to buy it because if you think
打算买它 ，因为如果你 认为
it's a ten dollar chip powers at $700
它在$ 700 十 块钱奇普·鲍尔斯
phone then of these big multiplier there
手机那么这些大的乘数有
so there's various options you can
所以有您可以各种选项
imagine one is what they call chemical
想象一个就是他们所说的化学
self-assembly where basically whatever
自组装，其中基本上什么
you're having sort of patterns itself
你有那种模式本身
just like the crystals would in a you
就像会在你的晶体
know in a block of or something like
知道块或类似的东西
that if you can imagine various chemical
如果你能想象的 各种化学
processes where things just form into
在事情刚刚组建成流程
the particulars aped so this is an area
细节模仿了，所以这是一个区域
that's been tried and worked on for
这就是被 尝试和努力上
electronics for several decades and
电子产品几十年，
never really succeeded yet but maybe
从来没有真正成功还没有，但也许
that's possible and another possibility
这是可能的，另一种可能
would be some interesting ideas in in
就 在 一些有趣的想法
multiple working with multiple layers at
与多个 层的多个工作
once so in particular one technology
一旦这样 一个 特别 的 技术
that's really been able to scale into
这是真正能够大规模进入
three dimensions are flash chips and
三个维度是闪存芯片和
that's part of the reason why my phone
这就是为什么我的 手机 的原因之一
has 64 gigabytes I'm not bragging I'm
拥有64 千兆字节，我不是吹牛，我
just telling you my phone has 64
只是告诉你我的 电话 64
gigabytes of memory you know why is
GB的内存，你知道是为什么
there so much memory a flash memory
有这么多的内存闪存
available on a quest as you know is sort
可在一个任务 ，你知道的是排序
of the storage of choice in a
选择的一个存储的
solid-state disk on cell phones nowadays
在手机固态硬盘如今
and so it's a it's based on
所以这是一个 它是基于
semiconductor devices so for example
半导体设备，从而例如
this is a electron micrograph of a chip
这是一个芯片的 电子显微镜照片
from samsung showing how they are able
三星展示他们如何能
to create a sort of three-dimensional
要创造 一种 三维
layering of memory cells so basically
存储器单元的分层 所以基本上
every spot in x y&z here is a one bits
在X Y＆Z这里的每点是 一个位
where it's actually two bits worth of
它实际上是两位值得的
of memory cell and there's some device
存储单元，并有一些设备
there that can store it and then there's
有可以储存它，然后 有
ways that you can access it to either
您可以将其接入方式或者
read it or write it and they're able to
阅读或书写它，他们能够
do with this whole layering but by using
做这个整体的层次感，但通过使用
only a fixed number of masking steps so
只有固定数量的掩蔽步骤，以便
basically what they start off with is
基本上他们开始什么了与IS
they build up layers without any masking
他们建立层没有任何掩蔽
and then they put some masks there and
然后他们把一些面具和有
then they zap down and they can sort of
然后他们扎普了，他们可以排序的
carve away of using basically ion beams
刻使用基本上离子束的离
to carve down wherever the mask is and
刻下来的地方 面具是和
pattern things then they can pour
图案的东西那么他们可以倒
various types of goop in there that will
在有各类GOOP那会
fill up these spaces and so by some
填补这些空间，因此被一些
patterning only at the very top layer
仅在最高层层图案化
they can actually create this
他们实际上可以创造这个
three-dimensional matrix of memory cells
存储器单元的 三维矩阵
and they can now the most recent
他们现在可以在最近的
technology gets about 48 layers and
技术得到约48层和
there's projections that they'll be able
还有的预测，他们将能够
to keep doing that at least through
继续这样做 ， 至少通过
several hundred layers so my point is
数百层，所以我的观点是
that you can actually do you don't
实际上你可以做你该做不
necessarily need to do masking at every
一定要做掩蔽在每
single layer to create a 3-dimensional
单个层以产生3维
structure now this doesn't scale in an
现在的结构，这并不规模在
obvious way to computers or
明显的方式向计算机或
microprocessors or anything with
微处理器或任何与
computation it relies very heavily on
计算它非常依赖
the fact that the particular circuit of
事实的具体电路
flash memory is very simple and fairly
闪存是 非常简单和公平
easy to build in this 3-dimensional
易在此建3维
structure but at least this is the kind
结构，但至少这是 种
of idea of what will have to happen if
什么将要发生，如果想法
we're going to get this kind of
我们会得到这样 的
integration
积分
but here's the harder one and this is a
但这里的困难之一，这是一个
problem just in general we're already up
问题只是 一般我们已经达
against the serious power issues now so
对严重的电力问题，现在这么
if I look at a modern phone the only
如果我看一个现代手机 的 唯一
drawers even when it's sort of working
抽屉 即使它的排序工作
hardest a couple of watts typically when
最难的一对夫妇瓦时，通常
it's just if you want to walk around if
它只是如果你想 ，如果走动
you want to have the battery be good for
你想拥有的电池 是好的
a day at a time it has to draw a lot
每天在同一时间它必须借鉴了很多
less power than that so typically when
比少的功率，从而典型地，当
your phones and standby it's only
你的手机和待机，这只是
drawing a few of a few milliwatts so
绘制几个几毫瓦左右
maybe a hundredth of a watt but when it
也许瓦的百分之一，但是，当它
needs to like you've just taken a
需要像你刚刚 拍摄的
picture and it wants to do some image
图片，它希望做一些图像
processing on it or you're taking a
它加工或你正在服用
video or something like that it can
视频或 类似 之能 事
crank up to a couple watts of power so
杀青功率的一对夫妇瓦等等
why can't it go more than that one is as
为什么不能去更重要的是一个是
I mentioned is the battery but the other
我提到的 是电池 ， 但 其他
is if your phone draws more than a few
就是如果你的手机吸引多了几个
watts then you won't really want to walk
瓦 那你 会不会真的不想走
around with it in your pocket because
围绕着 这个在 你的口袋里，因为
it'll be too hot so you know just
这将是太热了，所以你才知道
imagine a 25 watt light bulb if you put
想象一下25瓦的灯泡，如果你把
that in your pocket and walked around as
在你的口袋里 四处走了走 为
far as the extension cord would let you
据 延长线将 让你
that wouldn't feel too good
这不会感觉过分良好
so that limits the power isn't just
这样就限制 了功率 不只是
battery what so even if we come up with
电池什么，所以即使我们拿出
better bed resources the other thing is
更好的 床 资源的另一件事是
cooling so contrast that to the human
冷却，以便对比的是对人
brain is actually pretty amazing as a
大脑实际上是 作为一个 相当 惊人的
low power system so a human brain
低功耗的系统，人脑
contains roughly 64 billion neurons up
包含64个大致的神经元十亿 向上
but it and it draws a few tens of watts
但它和它吸引几十瓦
so more there's reasons than that so
所以更多有原因比 如此
it's a higher powered thing than a phone
它比手机高功率的事情
but it's still a very low power system
但它仍然是一个非常低的电源系统
so high power it's partly that's a
所以高功率它的一部分，这是一个
liquid-cooled system your brain circular
液体冷却 系统大脑圆形
your body circulation system puts a lot
你的身体循环系统提出了很多
of its work into keeping your brain from
其工作分成 从 保持 你的大脑
overheating and your body's metabolism
过热和你身体的新陈代谢
are you
你是
for example you guys sitting here each
例如你们坐在这里每
of you are drawing about sixty watts so
你正在绘制 关于 60瓦特所以
you like a 60 watt light bulb but about
你 喜欢60瓦的电灯泡，但关于
a quarter of that power is is powering
权力的四分之一被供电
the neurons in your brain so it's a
在 你的大脑 中的神经元 因此它是一个
fairly big chunk of the human energy
人体能量的相当大的块
budget is the brain which makes sense
预算是大脑这是有道理的
but it's still more power than we're
但它仍然更多的权力比我们
really going to allow in our portable
真的会允许在我们的便携式
devices if we don't want to our pits to
设备，如果我们不希望我们的进站
catch on fire and now the crazy thing is
着火，现在疯狂的事 是
but wait a minute I wanted to go up to
但是且慢，我想上去
10 to the 17th of these devices five
10到这些设备五十七
hundred thousand times more and I don't
十万次以上，我不
want to add any more power to this so
希望更多的功率添加到该如此
how is that going to happen well it's
这是怎么会发生 以及它的
certainly not going to happen with the
当然不会 与 发生
technology we have today that just can't
技术，我们今天只是不能
possibly meet those so we'll have to
可能满足这些，所以我们不得不
have some fairly radically different
有一些 相当截然不同
technology from a power perspective as
从电源的角度随着技术
well and misko is also not just for
好，MISKO也不仅仅是 为了
portable devices but even room size
便携设备 ，但即使房间大小
building sized computers for example
构建例如大小的电脑
right now the fastest computer in the
现在在最快的计算机
u.s. is at Oak Ridge National Labs
我们是在橡树岭国家实验室
it's called Titan a fastest in the world
它被称为泰坦 世界最快
it's in China and both of them draw
它在中国和他们两个画
roughly 10 megawatts okay of power so
大约10兆瓦的电力还好如此
the high-end supercomputers and one of
高端 的超级计算机和一个
the goals that the supercomputing people
目标是，超级计算人
talked about is to scale to what they
谈到是 扩展 到他们
call exascale meaning the ability to do
打电话百亿亿次级的意思做的能力
10 to the 18th operations per second
10至每秒18操作
whether they call flops floating-point
不管他们叫拖鞋浮点
operations per second so if you just
每秒操作，所以如果你只是
took Titan and said okay we want to make
把Titan和 说没关系，我们想使
it go a hundred times faster we'll just
他走了一百倍 快 我们就
put more so for example a Titan is built
把更多的这样的例子泰坦建
out of 28,000 microprocessors and 28,000
出28000个 微处理器28,000
GPUs so if we just go crank all that up
GPU的所以如果我们只是去杀青一切了
by a factor of 100 then you're talking
通过100倍，那么你在说
close to gigawatt of power so and just
接近 权力 吉瓦 左右，只是
roughly in rough terms the entire output
大致粗略估计整个输出
of the Hoover Dam is is would be enough
的胡佛水坝是是就 足够了
to power a 1 gigawatt system so our
驱动 一个 1个千兆瓦的系统，所以 我们
small nuclear power plant could do it
小核电站能做到这一点
too but the point is power is going to
过但 问题是电源要
be a big issue for both portable things
对于两个便携式的东西是个大问题
and for all of computing as we go
并为所有计算的，因为我们去
forward ok so that's sort of some of the
前确定，所以 这是排序的一些
technical challenges accommodation but
技术挑战，但住宿
another is an economic challenge is that
另一个是经济的挑战是 ，
it turns out that semiconductor business
事实证明， 半导体业务
has become more capital intensive and
已经变得更加资本密集型 和
harder to to sustain and so this is a
更难维持，因此这是一个
example of all the companies that we're
例如， 所有的 ， 我们是 该公司的
able to manufacture chips at different
能够在不同制造芯片
physical sizes so that it's a little bit
物理尺寸，使得它一点点
out of date the the latest chips are are
过时的 最新的芯片是
14 nanometers but you see that we're
14个纳米 但你看 ，我们是
basically down to four companies in the
基本上下降到 4家公司
world who have the wherewithal to
世界上谁有足够的资金来
manufacture state-of-the-art
制造状态的最先进的
semiconductor systems and and so and
半导体系统和等和
these are just to let you know tsmc is
这些 只是 让你知道 台积电
Taiwan semiconductor manufacturer
台湾 半导体制造商
they're huge in producing chips for
他们生产的芯片是巨大的
other customers basically what they call
其他客户 他们称之为基本上是什么
foundry so other designs come in so for
代工所以其他设计进来所以
example TSMC historically has been the
例如TSMC历史已经
main vendor for apple for almost all
主要供应商为苹果几乎所有
android phones are manufactured by tsmc
Android手机是由台积电制造
intel you know intel but they very much
英特尔要 知道英特尔，但 他们非常
rely completely for their business on on
完全 依靠 其上的业务
microprocessors and other things they
微处理器和其他的事情，他们
are that and they only with a small
是，他们只用小
exception only manufactured chips for
例外仅 制造芯片
their own use their own company
自己使用自己的公司
samsung as you know is in korea is a
三星你也知道是在韩国是一个
leading manufacturer and a lot of what
领先的制造商和很多 东西
they do is produce chips for samsung
他们做的是三星生产芯片
products but they also are one of the
产品，但他们也是的一个
biggest vendors of memory they also
内存也最大供应商
actually interestingly manufactures some
实际上有趣的是 制造一些
of the chips for apples so if you think
的芯片的苹果 ，所以如果你想
about the phone business who are the big
关于手机业务谁是大
competitors Samsung Apple but Samsung
竞争对手三星苹果但三星
actually builds Apple's chips Apple has
实际编制苹果的芯片 苹果
no manufacturing capabilities whatsoever
没有制造能力的任何
and then the fourth one is the one
然后将第四个是 一个
called Global Foundries which is a
所谓的格罗方德这是一个
company that sort of swept up all the
公司那种席卷了所有的
second string players and it's actually
第二弦乐演奏家它实际上是
owned by the sovereign wealth fund of
由主权财富基金拥有的
the Abu Dhabi so one of the United Arab
阿布扎比 阿联 这样一个
Emirates so really if you're you can
阿联酋航空 所以真的，如果你可以
think that there's two companies in Asia
认为有两家公司在 亚洲
one that's headquartered in Abu Dhabi
一个真实 总部设在阿布扎比
but it's actually physically other
但它实际上是身体其他
manufacturing facilities are in the u.s.
生产设施都在 美国
in Germany and in Singapore Intel all of
在德国和新加坡的英特尔所有的
its manufacturing is in the u.s. Taiwan
它的生产是 在 我们台湾
is at least through the leading edge all
至少穿过前缘所有
in Taiwan and Samsung they have a fab in
在台湾和三星 ，他们有一个晶圆厂
Texas and in Korea so anyways my point
得克萨斯州和韩国等等，反正我的观点
is
是
this isn't very many if you think of a
如果你认为的这是不是很多
300 billion dollar industry and sort of
300十亿美元的产业和 排序
where we're betting our future on you
我们打赌我们的未来你
only have four companies really that are
只有四家公司确实是
in the business right now is a little
在业务现在是一个小
bit scary and as you see if this trend
有点吓人 ，当你看看这个趋势
continues things wouldn't go well and
继续事情就不会顺利，
particularly if we want innovation and
特别是如果我们想创新，
progress to happen we need competition
进度发生，我们需要竞争
and if the number of companies dropped
如果企业数量下降
to small then the competition won't be
小那么竞争将不会 是
as significant either so these are
作为显著要么所以这些都是
interesting questions
有趣的问题
another thing that making life difficult
另一件事真难
and it's been making life difficult for
并且它已经 真难 为
the last ten years is what sometimes
过去的十年是什么 ，有时
referred to as Dennard scaling and this
称为 丹纳德缩放和这
is a term that you'll hear said nowadays
是一个术语，你会听到 说， 现在
and just a few years ago if you
而短短几年前 ，如果你
mentioned that term people would have no
提到这个词的人就没有
idea what you're talking about unless
知道你在说什么，除非有什么
you were pretty heavy into chips but
你是相当沉重到芯片 ，但
there's a fellow named Robert Denard who
有一位名叫罗伯特·德纳尔的家伙谁
had a long career at IBM he actually got
有很长的职业生涯，在他的IBM居然得了
his PhD here from Carnegie Tech in the
他的博士从这里卡内基技术在
1950s and among other things he invented
20世纪50年代和除其他事项外，他发明
the dynamic Ram
在动态RAM
so DRAM you know he's a guy but he wrote
所以DRAM，你知道他是一个人 ，但他写道：
a very interesting paper in in 1974 that
在1974年一个非常有趣的纸
sort of sketched out why it is that by
那种勾勒出为什么它是由
shrinking chips we a life gets better
缩小芯片我们生活变得更好
and it's a very simple model sort of
它是一个非常简单的模型排序
simple area geometry basics of Ohm's law
欧姆定律的简单区域几何基础
kind of stuff that that tells you what
样的东西， 告诉你什么
it's doing but he said imagine we can
它做什么，但他说，想象一下 ，我们可以
shrink a chip all the features on a chip
缩小芯片芯片上的所有功能
by a factor of some number K if you
通过如果在一定数目的K系数
typically really say 2 or the square
通常说真的2 或广场
root of 2 so if you can shrink in both x
2根，所以如果你可以在两个收缩X
and y directions by a factor of K and
和y 方向上由因子K和
this is a big important hand and we also
这是 一个重要的大手 ，我们也
reduce the supply voltage to the chip by
降低电源电压到芯片通过
that same factor then obviously we're
同样的因素 那么 显然我们
going to increase the number of devices
要增加 设备数量
by a factor of K squared right but also
通过因子K 方的权利，但也
we'll be able to make these run faster
我们将能够 使这些运行速度更快
and we'll be able to do it without
我们就可以做到这一点，而不
requiring more power per chip so if all
要求每个芯片更多的权力，所以如果一切
this scaling holds then we can get more
这个比例持有那么我们可以得到更多的
stuff on a chip run it faster and not
在一个芯片上的东西运行速度更快，而不是
use more power so that sort of the
使用更多的权力， 这样排序的
principle of Dennard scaling and that's
丹纳德的原则缩放，这就是
really what was followed by the industry
真的是其次是行业
for from about 75 to about
从约75至约
2004 this is a chart that shows how
2004年这是一个展示如何图表
technology progressed so the top curve
技术的进步使顶部曲线
here is Moore's law how many transistors
这里是摩尔定律 多少晶体管
were on a chip this next curve down was
是芯片这下曲线下降是在
how fast could a microprocessor go
如何能快速的微处理器去
running a single threat of execution and
运行单个 执行 威胁
you see it was following a sort of nice
你看，这是继一类的漂亮
steady growth curve what was the
稳增长曲线究竟是什么
frequency the clock frequency of the
频率的时钟频率
chip you saw also followed this nice
芯片你看见也跟着这个漂亮
growth curve until it hit about two
生长曲线，直到它触及约两
gigahertz how many watts per chip well
千兆赫多少瓦每块芯片以及
it's kind of variable but it was more or
它是一种可变的，但它是更多或
less it was going faster than Dennard
更少有人会比快 丹纳德
scaling predicted but still pretty
缩放预测，但仍然相当
reasonable and how many cores would we
合理和多少个核心，我们会
put on a chip well it was one for a
把一个芯片上， 以及它是一个用于
really long time and then they started
很长一段时间，然后他们开始
anymore so the main point to notice is
了，所以主要的一点要注意的 是
somewhere actually it was a right around
其实地方是围绕一个正确的
2005 things stopped progressing Moore's
2005年的事情进展停止 摩尔定律
law continues it continues today we can
法继续下去，今天，我们可以继续
get more stuff on a chip than before but
拿到芯片比以前但更多的东西
how fast a given thread goes has not
如何快速给定的线程去也没有
really improved much in the past of 10
真正的改善在10多过去
years and that's why the shark machines
多年来，这就是为什么鲨鱼机
which are already 5 years old are
这已经是5岁的
actually pretty viable computers which
实际上是相当可行的电脑，其
and the number of watts has leveled off
和瓦数已趋于稳定
not because that's the best thing
不是因为这是最好的事情
computing wise but that's because you
计算明智不过那是因为你
just can't afford to the cost of the
只是不掉的成本
actual electricity cost as well as all
实际的电力成本， 以及所有
the requirements for cooling and things
冷却和事物的要求
that comes with increased power and so
这无疑提高功率等
that combination is the reason why we've
该组合就是为什么我们以前做的原因
gone multi-core that we couldn't get
走了多核心， 我们无法得到
improved single-threaded performance but
改进的单线程性能，但
we could improve the number of
我们可以改善的数量
transistors
晶体管
chip so what do we do we just make more
芯片所以我们做什么 ，我们只是让更多
cores and so my so so some will tell you
核心等 我那么那么有些人会告诉 你
that Moore's law is already dead in the
摩尔定律是在 已经死了
sense that for a while there is a sort
感觉， 有一段时间是 一种
of miraculous things just kept getting
神奇的事情就一直得到
better and better every year because of
每年都有 越来越 好 ，因为
Moore's law and now we're already in an
摩尔定律，现在我们已经在
era that even though the transistor
时代，即使晶体管
density part of Moore's law holds some
摩尔定律的密度部分持有一些
of these other performance factors have
这些其他性能因素
not improved so it's in getting
没有改良，它是在 获得
difficult to sort of use this technology
难以理清的使用这项技术
to make things faster and more powerful
使事情更快 ，更强大
and so I'll mention for example part of
所以我会 提 出 实例部分
the reason why this phone actually I
之所以这款手机其实我
don't know how many transistors are in
不知道有多少晶体管在
this phone but if you think at two
这款手机 ，但如果你想在两个
billion transistors the model before
十亿个晶体管的模型前
that had 1 billion you say well what
在具有1个十亿，你说好了什么
what are all these transistors doing
什么是所有这些晶体管做
part of what they've done is and part of
他们做了什么部分是与部分
the reason they're able to keep the
他们能够保持的原因
power down is a lot of what's on a they
断电是很多对他们有什么
call the the chip now it's not called a
现在所说的芯片它不叫
microprocessor it's called a system on a
微处理器，它被称为系统上
chip
芯片
because embedded on it will be a couple
因为嵌入这将是一对夫妇
of arm microprocessors several graphic
的ARM 微处理器几个图形
processing units to handle the video the
处理单元处理视频
image processing and other specialized
图像处理和其他专门
pieces of hardware that are only used
硬件的部件，它们 仅用于
for very specific things so for example
非常具体的东西 ，所以 例如
there's a JPEG encoding and decoding is
有一个JPEG 编码和解码
directly integrated into Hardware on
直接集成到硬件上
this chip there's a actually some
该芯片有一个竟有些
special logic for when you take
当你采取特殊的逻辑
panoramic shots and then you merge those
全景照片 ，然后你合并这些
all together which I don't know about
都在一起，我 不知道
you but I don't do that very often but
你，但我不 这样做， 很多时候，但
there's still some special dedicated
还是有一些特殊的专用
Hardware on those chips to do that
这些芯片的硬件做
because it takes a lot of power
因为它 需要大量的电能
otherwise so in general if you can take
否则 因此一般来说，如果你可以采取
a some compute computing and turn it
一个有些计算计算，并把它
from software and migrate it to hardware
从软件，并将其移植 到 硬件
you get a big performance increase and a
你得到一个大的性能提升和
major power reduction so they're putting
各大电力减少，使他们就会把
more stuff on a chip not to give you
在一个芯片上更多的东西不给你
more possible
更多的可能
powerful processor but to be able to do
强大的处理器，但要能做到
more stuff at lower power so that's why
在低功率更多的东西所以这就是为什么
these chips get more so my point is that
这些芯片得到更多，所以我的观点是，
they're already sort of we're already in
他们 已经那种 我们已经在
an era when the driving reason for
一个时代当驱动原因
Moore's law isn't so much to get raw
摩尔定律是不是 要拿到原
performance out of these systems but to
性能这些系统， 但对
give you more features various sorts
给你更多的功能，不同的种类
okay
好的
so looking to the future then as I said
所以展望未来，然后 我说
it you can look at since 65 it's been a
它 ，你可以看一下，因为65 它是一个
very long set of incremental
很长设置的增量
improvements to get from the chips of
改进从芯片获得
Gordon Moore's early career to where we
戈登·穆尔的早期职业生涯中，我们在那里
are today we got more stuff on a chip
今天我们得到了更多的东西在一个芯片上
vastly more capable much more affordable
得多能够更实惠
huge impact on it but from a technology
它不过从技术的巨大影响
point of view it's been a fairly
的 角度 来看 它是一个相当
incremental road to travel we can see
增量公路旅行，我们可以看到
that that's not going to work in the
那这 不会 在工作
future we're not going to be able to
未来我们不打算要能
scale transistor logic to the level that
规模晶体管逻辑到水平
you'd need to keep this going so at
你需要保持这是怎么回事因此在
least two-dimensional semiconductor
至少二维的半导体
chips aren't going to carry the way so
芯片不会携带的方式，使
they sort of issues then and you and
他们的排序问题，然后你和
your careers will be dealing with these
你的职业生涯将处理这些
is will we be able to build systems of
是，我们才能 打造系统
this complexity in a way that's
这种复杂的方式，是
commercially viable because if it's not
商业上可行的，因为如果它不
economically viable it's just not going
经济上可行它只是不会
to happen and power is going to be a
发生 和权力 将 是 一个
huge problem as we go along and then you
巨大的问题，因为我们一起 ，然后你 走
know what would it mean if you actually
知道这将 意味着 什么 ，如果你真的
had 10 to the 17th I can't think of what
有10到17，我不能想到什么
possible capabilities this would give us
可能这个功能将会给 我们
that we'd actually want use but again if
我们预期的要如果使用，但再次
I don't think Gordon Moore would have
我不认为戈登·穆尔将有
thought back in 60 if you look at the 65
在60位认为回来，如果你看65
paper I recommend you do he actually did
本文中，我建议你这样做，他实际上做
predict things like personal computers
预测之类的个人电脑
and cell phones believe it or not it's
和手机 相不相信它的
really true um so he was definitely
真的嗯，所以他肯定
pretty good but for me I can't predict
不错，但对我来说，我不能预测
what I
我什么
have in 50 years what I do with it and
有50年我做什么与它
then for more the software people you
那么对于更多的 软件 ，你的人
know what what mean will there be
知道意味着什么会不会有
programming we certainly won't be
编程中，我们肯定不会
writing lines of code in C in order to
编写的代码行中的沸点，以
power systems like this so what will
动力系统是这样那么要怎么做
that mean for the future those are all
这意味着未来这些都是
big questions that you and this point of
大问题，你和这个点
your careers get to look forward to so I
你的职业生涯去期待，所以我
wish you the best in doing that
祝你 在做的是 最好 的